<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>messages from ENV</title>
 <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de</id>
 <updated>2021-11-20T12:29:46-06:00</updated>
 <author>
   <name>Daniel Krippner</name>
   <uri>https://www.danielkrippner.de</uri>
   <email>dk.mailbox@gmx.net</email>
 </author>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Mac Keyboard</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard</id>
   <updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m probably going to have a trend in my Apple-related posts, where I’m going from mostly negative as I get used to things to more positive as I’m coming to grips with the system. So let’s get the biggest gripe out of the way first: the keyboard layout. I knew...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Apple Products</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/apple"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/apple</id>
   <updated>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After spending almost all of my over 25 years long ‘computing life’ with Windows and especially Linux systems, with the recent advent of M1 silicon and in light of the constant superiority complex that Apple users project into their surroundings, I decided it was time to finally take a peek...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Add a second hall sensor to Sonoff SV Garage Door Opener</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/sonoffsensor"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/sonoffsensor</id>
   <updated>2021-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago I was in the process of automating things around the house, having recently discovered Raspberry Pi-driven home automation and the associated potential for “fiddling with things”. During this phase, I came across the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hagensieker.com/wordpress/2019/02/18/sonoff-sv-for-garage-door-opener/&quot;&gt;John’s Tech Blog writeup on how to automate garage door openers...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Switch home assistant entity via command-line</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/hassapi"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/hassapi</id>
   <updated>2021-05-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last few days we paused on the journey, doing real-world things involving a guitar and some frustration. Tonight, there was an idea I wanted to follow up on: when I cobbled together my Raspi k8s cluster, I grabbed a zigbee power switch I had lying around, to be able...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Jekyll build via github Actions</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/jekyllgithub"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/jekyllgithub</id>
   <updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not quite ‘professional’ yet - but, another step. We created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AnotherDaniel/messages-env/blob/main/.github/workflows/build_package.yml&quot;&gt;github Actions configuration&lt;/a&gt; that builds our jekyll site on commit, then packages the nginx container (from arm64) and pushes it to the github package registry.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Why we did this, instead of continuing running the build pipe on our...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>A jekyll build pipe at home</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/jekyllbuildpipe"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/jekyllbuildpipe</id>
   <updated>2021-04-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So what’s down? Well. Working on a jekyll publication pipeline, we had a bit of hindsight-stupid puzzling-fun with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll build&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;-b&lt;/strong&gt; switch. That thing changes the &lt;strong&gt;site.baseurl&lt;/strong&gt;, not the &lt;strong&gt;site.url&lt;/strong&gt;! Which took some thinking/experimenting to find out from the fact that this switch caused the site to...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>The Journey</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/journey"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/journey</id>
   <updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Due to an interesting constellation at work - a new project, with new partners and space for arbitrary ideas - I have found new motivation to spend evening time for learning and playing. I always wanted to get hands-on with this “cloud stuff”, dockerizing things, working with k8s, ansible, maybe...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Deploy Deconz zigbee control software via docker</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/dockerdeconz"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/dockerdeconz</id>
   <updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu provides a server (headless) version that also is available for ARM devices - this is a great option if you want a 64bit OS on your Raspberry 3 (of course it works equally well on 4th-gen Raspberry boards). This motivated me to move my home automation Raspi over onto...</content>
 </entry>

 

</feed>