<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>messages from ENV</title>
 <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de</id>
 <updated>2022-02-12T15:55:27-06:00</updated>
 <author>
   <name>Daniel Krippner</name>
   <uri>https://www.danielkrippner.de</uri>
   <email>dk.mailbox@gmx.net</email>
 </author>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Simple Scanning Station</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/scanningstation"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/scanningstation</id>
   <updated>2022-02-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mostly out of Corona-induced boredom I decided I wanted a document scanning pipeline to get any relevant paperwork into a document management system like doscpell, with as little effort (both cost-wise and from a UX perspective) as possible. So I built a simple and hands-off scanning station with my raspberry...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>3 Mac keyboards</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard</id>
   <updated>2022-02-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quick interlude: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard&quot;&gt;Apple keyboard love&lt;/a&gt; seems to go both ways. A couple of weeks ago, the keyboard of the barely 2 months old M1 Macbook Pro died. Just like that - no keypresses registered any more, backlight off, rebooting etc didn’t to anything. The touchpad continued to funtion...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Of course we (only) do AirPrint!</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/airprint"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/airprint</id>
   <updated>2021-12-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After approximately one month, the Apple journey is going well. Even picking up speed one could say, as I’m beginning to feel comfortable, or even at home a lot of the time. Still not closer to appreciating how the application switcher works, though ;-)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I’ve done a full ecosystem...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Two weeks of Apple</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/after-two-weeks"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/after-two-weeks</id>
   <updated>2021-11-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been two weeks now since I started to grow my Apple garden - one of the M1 MacBooks, a current iPhone, and recently a M1 iPad to complement my core device needs. The major rants I just had to get off my chest were about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard&quot;&gt;keyboard layout&lt;/a&gt;,...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>MacOS Application Switcher</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/appswitcher"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/appswitcher</id>
   <updated>2021-11-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The MacOS application switcher is my second-biggest gripe after the keyboard layout. I am getting better with remembering which modifier keys to press when, as expected. So let’s get to the second thing that will probably pale with routine: the Application Switcher (the thing you get when pressing command-Tab).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Mac Keyboard</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard</id>
   <updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m probably going to have a trend in my Apple-related posts, where I’m going from mostly negative as I get used to things to more positive as I’m coming to grips with the system. So let’s get the biggest gripe out of the way first: the keyboard layout. I knew...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Apple Products</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/apple"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/apple</id>
   <updated>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After spending almost all of my over 25 years long ‘computing life’ with Windows and especially Linux systems, with the recent advent of M1 silicon and in light of the constant superiority complex that Apple users project into their surroundings, I decided it was time to finally take a peek...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Add a second hall sensor to Sonoff SV Garage Door Opener</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/sonoffsensor"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/sonoffsensor</id>
   <updated>2021-05-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago I was in the process of automating things around the house, having recently discovered Raspberry Pi-driven home automation and the associated potential for “fiddling with things”. During this phase, I came across the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hagensieker.com/wordpress/2019/02/18/sonoff-sv-for-garage-door-opener/&quot;&gt;John’s Tech Blog writeup on how to automate garage door openers...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Switch home assistant entity via command-line</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/hassapi"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/hassapi</id>
   <updated>2021-05-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last few days we paused on the journey, doing real-world things involving a guitar and some frustration. Tonight, there was an idea I wanted to follow up on: when I cobbled together my Raspi k8s cluster, I grabbed a zigbee power switch I had lying around, to be able...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Jekyll build via github Actions</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/jekyllgithub"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/jekyllgithub</id>
   <updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not quite ‘professional’ yet - but, another step. We created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AnotherDaniel/messages-env/blob/main/.github/workflows/build_package.yml&quot;&gt;github Actions configuration&lt;/a&gt; that builds our jekyll site on commit, then packages the nginx container (from arm64) and pushes it to the github package registry.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Why we did this, instead of continuing running the build pipe on our...</content>
 </entry>

 

</feed>