<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>messages from ENV</title>
 <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de</id>
 <updated>2022-05-22T15:32:27-05:00</updated>
 <author>
   <name>Daniel Krippner</name>
   <uri>https://www.danielkrippner.de</uri>
   <email>dk.mailbox@gmx.net</email>
 </author>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Using my own container registry</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/use-own-registry"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/use-own-registry</id>
   <updated>2022-05-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This will be a short update - just to be consistent about where I describe my configuration gimmicks if I ever need to look things up in the future :-) The problem that is solved in this article is the fact that the Docker Hub free tier only allows hosting...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Backing up a nextcloud file share via webdav</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/nextcloud-backup"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/nextcloud-backup</id>
   <updated>2022-05-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first question after having &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danielkrippner.de/raspi-NAS&quot;&gt;set up a NAS&lt;/a&gt;: what could we use it for? Mine is already running a timemachine server, but that’s barely making a dent in the disk space utilization of the system. Well, the one entity that stores almost all of our pictures, music, documents,...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>NAS setup with an Argon EON</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/raspi-NAS"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/raspi-NAS</id>
   <updated>2022-05-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Looks like I am on a kind of ‘Argon run’ this quarter: since I upgraded the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danielkrippner.de/M2-for-raspi&quot;&gt;Argon One case to run off an M.2 drive&lt;/a&gt;, due to a stroke of lucky timing I managed to get an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.argon40.com/products/argon-eon-pi-nas&quot;&gt;Argon Eon NAS case&lt;/a&gt; at a very fair price point -...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Migrating a Raspi setup to USB/SATA</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/M2-for-raspi"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/M2-for-raspi</id>
   <updated>2022-04-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My home IT infrastructure currently runs off a single trusty Raspberry Pi 4B - that’s around 30 containerized apps from DNS filter/proxy, Home Assistant et al for home automation, document management system, to printer proxy, vehicle data logger, and more. The Pi is an amazingly good fit for this purpose,...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Nextcloud CLI shell script</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/nextcloud-cli"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/nextcloud-cli</id>
   <updated>2022-02-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the recent instantiation of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danielkrippner.de/scanningstation&quot;&gt;simple scanning station&lt;/a&gt;, there is now another data sink in my home network that wants backup. And in the case of the docspell database, we’re looking at quite relevant data, so a backup definitely is called for. Where backups are concerned I am...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Simple Scanning Station</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/scanningstation"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/scanningstation</id>
   <updated>2022-02-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mostly out of Corona-induced boredom I decided I wanted a document scanning pipeline to get any relevant paperwork into a document management system like doscpell, with as little effort (both cost-wise and from a UX perspective) as possible. So I built a simple and hands-off scanning station with my raspberry...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>3 Mac keyboards</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard</id>
   <updated>2022-02-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quick interlude: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard&quot;&gt;Apple keyboard love&lt;/a&gt; seems to go both ways. A couple of weeks ago, the keyboard of the barely 2 months old M1 Macbook Pro died. Just like that - no keypresses registered any more, backlight off, rebooting etc didn’t to anything. The touchpad continued to funtion...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Of course we (only) do AirPrint!</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/airprint"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/airprint</id>
   <updated>2021-12-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After approximately one month, the Apple journey is going well. Even picking up speed one could say, as I’m beginning to feel comfortable, or even at home a lot of the time. Still not closer to appreciating how the application switcher works, though ;-)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I’ve done a full ecosystem...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>Two weeks of Apple</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/after-two-weeks"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/after-two-weeks</id>
   <updated>2021-11-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been two weeks now since I started to grow my Apple garden - one of the M1 MacBooks, a current iPhone, and recently a M1 iPad to complement my core device needs. The major rants I just had to get off my chest were about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.danielkrippner.de/mackeyboard&quot;&gt;keyboard layout&lt;/a&gt;,...</content>
 </entry>

 

 <entry>
   <title>MacOS Application Switcher</title>
   <link href="https://www.danielkrippner.de/appswitcher"/>
   <id>https://www.danielkrippner.de/appswitcher</id>
   <updated>2021-11-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The MacOS application switcher is my second-biggest gripe after the keyboard layout. I am getting better with remembering which modifier keys to press when, as expected. So let’s get to the second thing that will probably pale with routine: the Application Switcher (the thing you get when pressing command-Tab).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2...</content>
 </entry>

 

</feed>